<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Craig Brinkerhoff</title>
    <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Craig Brinkerhoff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>©craigbrinkerhoff</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A First Look at River Discharge Estimation From SWOT Satellite Observations</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_18/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_18/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2024GL114185
JournalGeophysical Research Letters
AuthorsAndreadis, Konstantinos M., Coss, Steve P., Durand, Michael, Gleason, Colin J., Simmons, Travis T., Tebaldi, Nikki, Bjerklie, David M., Brinkerhoff, Craig, Dudley, Robert W., Gejadze, Igor, Larnier, Kevin, Malaterre, Pierre-Olivier, Oubanas, Hind, Allen, George H., Bates, Paul D., David, C&#39;edric H., Domeneghetti, Alessio, Elmi, Omid, Marc, Luciana Fenoglio, Prata de Moraes Frasson, Renato, Friedmann, Elisa, Garambois, Pierre-Andr&#39;e, Gehring, Jaclyn, Getirana, Augusto, Hughes, Marissa, Lee, Jonghyun, Matte, Pascal, Minear, J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Importance of Source Data in River Network Connectivity Modeling: A Review</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_16/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1002/lno.12706
JournalLimnology and Oceanography
AuthorsBrinkerhoff, C.B.
AbstractRiver network connectivity (RC) describes the hydrologic exchange of water, nutrients, sediments, and pollutants between the river channel and other ``sites’’ via heterogenous flowpaths along the river corridor. As water moves downstream it carries these constituents, creating a stream-to-ocean continuum of connectivity that regulates global water, carbon, and nutrient cycling. River network connectivity models have developed over many decades, culminating in recent years with network-scale RC models that explicitly simulate the transport and exchange of water and elements from headwaters to coasts, sometimes requiring models to contain tens of millions of river reaches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward Modeling Continental-Scale Inland Water Carbon Dioxide Emissions</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_17/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_17/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2024AV001294
JournalAGU Advances
AuthorsSaccardi, Brian, Brinkerhoff, Craig B., Gleason, Colin J., Winnick, Matthew J.
AbstractAbstract Inland waters emit significant amounts of carbon dioxide (CO2) to the atmosphere; however, the global magnitude and source distribution of inland water CO2 emissions remain uncertain. These fluxes have previously been statistically upscaled by independently estimating dissolved CO2 concentrations and gas exchange velocities to calculate fluxes. This scaling, while robust and defensible, has known limitations in representing carbon source limitations and spatial variability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ephemeral Stream Water Contributions to United States Drainage Networks</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_15/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_15/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1126/science.adg9430
JournalScience
AuthorsBrinkerhoff, C.B., Gleason, Colin J., Kotchen, Matthew J., Kysar, Douglas A., Raymond, Peter A.
AbstractEphemeral streams flow only in direct response to precipitation and are ubiquitous landscape features. However, little is known about their influence on downstream rivers. Here, we modeled ephemeral stream water contributions to the contiguous United States network of more than 20 million rivers, lakes, and reservoirs, finding that ephemeral streams contribute, on average, 55% of the discharge exported from regional river systems, as defined by the United States Geological Survey.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Proglacial Headwater Streams in High Mountain Asia Using PlanetScope Imagery</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_14/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_14/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2024.114124
JournalRemote Sensing of Environment
AuthorsFlores, J.A., Gleason, C.J., Brinkerhoff, C.B., Harlan, M.E., Lummus, M.M., Stearns, L.A., Feng, D.
AbstractHeadwater streams transport nutrients, sediment, and mineral-rich groundwater downstream. In High Mountain Asia (HMA), headwater streams also funnel glacier and snow melt to sustain continuous water supply for the downstream region. These channels remain poorly mapped because of their inaccessibility and because they are smaller than the resolution of Landsat (30~m) and Sentinel-2 (10~m).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning Lakes Into River Gauges Using the LakeFlow Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_13/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2023GL103924
JournalGeophysical Research Letters
AuthorsRiggs, R.M., Allen, G.H., Brinkerhoff, C.B., Sikder, Md.S., Wang, J.
AbstractRivers and lakes are intrinsically connected waterbodies yet they are rarely used to hydrologically constrain one another with remote sensing. Here we begin to bridge the gap between river and lake hydrology with the introduction of the LakeFlow algorithm. LakeFlow uses river-lake mass conservation and observations from the Surface Water and Ocean Topography (SWOT) satellite to provide river discharge estimates of lake and reservoir inflows and outflows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Framework for Estimating Global River Discharge From the Surface Water and Ocean Topography Satellite Mission</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_12/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_12/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2021WR031614
JournalWater Resources Research
AuthorsDurand, M. T., Gleason, C.J., Pavelsky, T. M., Frasson, R. P. M., Turmon, M., David, C.H., Altenau, E. H., Tebaldi, N., Larnier, K., Monnier, J., Malaterre, P.O., Oubanas, H., Allen, G.H., Astifan, B., Brinkerhoff, C.B., Bates, P.D., Bjerklie, D., Coss, S., Dudley, R., Fenoglio, L., Garambois, P.-A., Getirana, A., Lin, P., Margulis, S.A., Matte, P., Minear, J.T., Muhebwa, A., Pan, M., Peters, D.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inversion of River Discharge from Remotely Sensed River Widths: A Critical Assessment at Three-Thousand Global River Gauges</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_11/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_11/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2023.113489
JournalRemote Sensing of Environment
AuthorsLin, P., Feng, D., Gleason, C.J., Pan, M., Brinkerhoff, C.B., Yang, X., Beck, H.E., Frasson, R. P. M.
AbstractAccurately estimating river discharge from satellite-derived river hydraulic variables (e.g., width, height, and slope) is the overarching goal of the remote sensing of discharge (RSQ) community. Numerous past studies have developed and intercompared different RSQ algorithms to demonstrate their feasibility, yet relatively few have focused on assessing how the RSQ algorithms are adapted to a wide range of rivers globally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Watershed DOC Uptake Occurs Mostly in Lakes in the Summer and in Rivers in the Winter</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_10/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1002/lno.12306
JournalLimnology and Oceanography
AuthorsMaavara, T.M., Brinkerhoff, C.B., Hosen, J.D., Aho, K.S., Logozzo, L.A., Saiers, J.E., Stubbins, A., Raymond, P.A.
AbstractRiver networks transport dissolved organic carbon (DOC) from terrestrial uplands to the coastal ocean. The extent to which a reach or lake within a river network uptakes DOC depends on the stream order, the seasonal conditions, and the flow. At the watershed scale, it remains unclear whether DOC uptake is dominated by biological processes such as respiration, or abiotic processes like photomineralization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Remotely Sensing River Greenhouse Gas Exchange Velocity Using the SWOT Satellite</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_9/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2022GB007419
JournalGlobal Biogeochemical Cycles
AuthorsBrinkerhoff, C.B., Gleason, C.J., Zappa, C.J., Raymond, P.A., Harlan, M.E.
AbstractTwo decades of research has shown that the global river network emits significant amounts of greenhouse gas. Despite much progress, there is still large uncertainty in the temporal dynamics of gas exchange and thus carbon emissions to the atmosphere. Much of this uncertainty stems from a lack of existing tools for studying the spatiotemporal dynamics of gas exchange velocity (the rate of this diffusive transport).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Controls on DOC Reaction Versus Export in Watersheds: A Damk&#34;ohler Number Analysis</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_8/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2021GB007278
JournalGlobal Biogeochemical Cycles
AuthorsLiu, S., Maavara, T.M., Brinkerhoff, C.B., Raymond, P.A.
AbstractThe relative capacity for watersheds to eliminate or export reactive constituents has important implications on aquatic ecosystem ecology and biogeochemistry. Removal efficiency depends on factors that affect either the reactivity or advection of a constituent within river networks. Here, we characterized Damk&#34;ohler number (Da) for dissolved organic carbon (DOC) uptake in global river networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Importance of Hydrology in Routing Terrestrial Carbon to the Atmosphere via Global Streams and Rivers</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_7/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2106322119
JournalProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
AuthorsLiu, S., Kuhn, C., Amatulli, G., Aho, K.S., Butman, D.E., Allen, G.H., Lin, P., Pan, M., Yamazaki, D., Brinkerhoff, C.B., Gleason, C.J., Xia, X., Raymond, P.A.
AbstractThe magnitude of stream and river carbon dioxide (CO2) emission is affected by seasonal changes in watershed biogeochemistry and hydrology. Global estimates of this flux are, however, uncertain, relying on calculated values for CO2 and lacking spatial accuracy or seasonal variations critical for understanding macroecosystem controls of the flux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Photomineralization of Dissolved Organics Matter in Temperate Rivers</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_6/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_6/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2021JG006402
JournalJournal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences
AuthorsMaavara, T.M., Logozzo, L.A., Stubbins, A., Aho, K.S., Brinkerhoff, C.B., Hosen, J.D., Raymond, P.A.
AbstractSunlight can oxidize dissolved organic carbon (DOC) to dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) in freshwaters. The importance of complete photooxidation, or photomineralization, as a sink for DOC remains unclear in temperate rivers, as most estimates are restricted to lakes, high latitude rivers, and coastal river plumes. In this study, we construct a model representing over 75,000 river reaches in the Connecticut River Watershed (CRW), USA, to calculate spectrally resolved photomineralization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Factors Controlling the Error Characteristics of the Surface Water and Ocean Topography Mission Discharge Estimates</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_5/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2020WR028519
JournalWater Resources Research
AuthorsFrasson, R. P. M., Durand, M.T., Larnier, K., Gleason, C.J., Andreadis, K.M., Hagemann, M. W., Dudley, R., Bjerklie, D., Oubanas, H., Garambois, P.-A., Malaterre, P.O., Lin, P., Pavelsky, T. M., Monnier, J., Brinkerhoff, C.B., David, C.H.
AbstractThe Surface Water and Ocean Topography (SWOT) satellite mission will measure river width, water surface elevation, and slope for rivers wider than 50–100 m. SWOT observations will enable estimation of river discharge by using simple flow laws such as the Manning-Strickler equation, complementing in situ streamgages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lake Morphometry and River Network Controls on Evasion of Terrestrially Sourced Headwater CO2</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_4/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_4/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2020GL090068
JournalGeophysical Research Letters
AuthorsBrinkerhoff, C.B., Raymond, P.A., Maavara, T.M., Ishitsuka, Y., Aho, K. S., Gleason, C. J.
AbstractLakes are central components of the inland water system distinct from, yet inextricably connected to, river networks. Currently, existing network-scale biogeochemistry research, although robust, typically treats each of these components separately or reductively. Here, we incorporate lake morphometry into a fully connected stream/lake network for the Connecticut River watershed and model potential evasion of terrestrially sourced headwater CO2 as transported through the network, ignoring in-stream production.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Remote River Discharge Estimation Using Reach-Scale Geomorphology</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_3/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2020WR027949
JournalWater Resources Research
AuthorsBrinkerhoff, C.B., Gleason, C. J., Feng, D., Lin, P.
AbstractRecent advances in remote sensing and the upcoming launch of the joint NASA/CNES/CSA/UKSA Surface Water and Ocean Topography (SWOT) satellite point toward improved river discharge estimates in ungauged basins. Existing discharge methods rely on prior river knowledge&#39;&#39; to infer parameters not directly measured from space. Here, we show that discharge estimation is improved by classifying and parameterizing rivers based on their unique geomorphology and hydraulics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the Assimilation of SWOT Observations With Hydraulic Geometry Relations</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_2/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2019WR026611
JournalWater Resources Research
AuthorsAndreadis, K.M., Brinkerhoff, C. B., Gleason, C. J.
AbstractThe Surface Water Ocean Topography (SWOT) satellite mission expected to launch in 2021 will offer a unique opportunity to map river discharge at an unprecedented spatial resolution globally from observations of water surface elevation, width, and slope. Because river discharge will not be directly observed from SWOT, a number of algorithms of varying complexity have been developed to estimate discharge from SWOT observables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reconciling At-a-Station and at-Many-Stations Hydraulic Geometry Through River-Wide Geomorphology</title>
      <link>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://craigbrinkerhoff.netlify.app/publication/paper_1/</guid>
      <description>DOIhttps://doi.org/10.1029/2019GL084529
JournalGeophysical Research Letters
AuthorsBrinkerhoff, C.B., Gleason, C. J., Ostendorf, D. W.
AbstractAt-many-stations hydraulic geometry (AMHG), while useful for estimating river discharge from satellite data, remains empirical and has yet to be reconciled with the at-a-station hydraulic geometry (AHG) from which it was originally derived. Here we present evidence, using United States Geological Survey field measurements of channel hydraulics for 155 rivers, that AMHG can be hydraulically and geomorphically reconciled with AHG.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
